Welcome back. You are listening to
Golden Rule Radio, your weekly
discussion of the precious metals
markets and the markets closely
associated with the metals. I'm Tory,
alongside Miles and Rob, and together we
have over 80 years of experience
advising on and brokering the precious
metals. And each week the three of us
want to provide a technical analysis, as
well as a fundamental analysis of the
metals, as well as the news that helps
move and predict these markets. As
always, we're going to jump right in and
give you a weekly recap. Recording today
on Wednesday, March 11th. Miles, take it
away. Kind of a quick recap this week,
Tory. Appreciate it. As most everything
is kind of parked right in their trading
ranges. So, we'll kick it off with gold.
Gold is up about half a percent over the
past week. Currently sitting at $5,180.
Silver, actually silver putting in the
best numbers this week, up about 4%
from our recording last Wednesday,
sitting just under 86 at $85.94.
The other white metals we like to keep
an eye on, first platinum. Platinum also
up about 2%.
Sitting at $2,166.
And the sister metal to platinum,
palladium, which is starting to continue
to stretch that ratio out between the
two. Palladium is down 2%, $1,611.
Now about 500 bucks below platinum. The
paper markets, the S&P down 1% this week
to 6,775
points. Although for me, that's not the
whole story in the equities market. And
I want to carve a few minutes out to
talk about that here before we finish
the show. And finally, I know we're
going to carve some time out to talk
about the dollar. The dollar is up a
staggering 0.1%
so a tenth of a percent over the past
week, but it is looking strong currently
sitting at 99.22
and again at least short-term it's
looking strong, but we'll want to see if
that's true in the long term as well. So
guys, where do you want to start off
this week? Well, let's talk about the
trading range in gold.
Where do you see the base and where's
resistance?
So you're looking at a climbing trading
range in gold again following the big
run up back at the end of January, the
big fall that we've talked about to
death. So we're not going to go too deep
into that, but Rob we're continuing that
stair-step we've been talking about
bouncing up the hill and staying within
the range. You would argue we're kind of
at the bottom of the range now. I'd say
probably we've got another 40-50 dollars
down where you could argue that gold is
still maintaining the same bullish range
up, but if we do turn at the bottom,
there is a very good probability the
next time we go up to the top we're
looking at a potential double top or
breakout. So the momentum continues to
climb, the range continues to be held,
but it's a very strong bullish range and
we're kind of coming to decision point
here I would argue in the next couple
weeks in gold. Are we going to break
into the 56-5700s
and continue to climb especially on some
of the geopolitical news that we've got
coming out right now or are we going to
see gold start to languish here and
maybe start putting in a couple lower
lows which is obviously also possible.
So decision point in gold is probably
pending in a very short period of time.
Well, we talk about technicals like what
you discussed and Tory's going to dive
into fundamentals, but you know me I've
always liked the seasonals and what is
the strongest season for the metals
guys? Spring.
>> We're in it. We're in it. So, I think
that leans me towards a move higher,
either a double top or like you said,
Miles, a breakout. Well, we better see
it pretty soon. Honestly, I mean, time's
flying, but if you look at the last 3
weeks, we've been kind of stuck. Yeah,
Torries getting impatient. Yeah, I know.
Again.
But, yeah. I mean, 5200 is kind of where
we've been glued.
>> Yeah. Other than the 5400
roughly mark with the Iran conflict
breaking out, we don't want to go below
5000, and we really don't want to go
above 5250. You know, that's kind of
really where we've been for a few weeks,
and
>> Well, we want it to go above 5250, but
the market seems to be topped out.
>> Well, yeah, it needs more It needs more
momentum, right, Miles?
>> Something to move it, as Miles would
say. And so, Miles will tell us exactly
where it's going to go next. Of course,
he will. He just won't tell us why or
when.
How soon?
Do I have to keep waiting long, Miles?
Uh when? When it happens. It'll happen
when it happens. Silver, though, I mean,
I'm shocked. I got to say, the fact that
that silver's up again 4% this week. I
mean, it also had that spike. We did get
up to the 96. It didn't last at all.
With silver, about 90 has been a
ceiling. We've hit our head there, and
it doesn't want to really break through.
And then, coming down, roughly 78 to 90
has been our range in that same period
of time the last few weeks that gold's
been Right.
>> chopping sideways. And we're up 4% in
the last week, but what fundamental
event happened in the last week to see
silver strengthen?
China opened up. They were shut down for
2 weeks during Chinese New Year. So, not
quite the momentum that I had hoped for,
but you know, 4% is better than a sharp
stick in the eye. Did they allow trading
in silver? Cuz you know, back at the end
of January, they weren't a big fan of
trading silver there for 24 hours. So,
they opened back up and they allowed
their people to trade silver. Well,
that's How very generous of them.
>> Isn't that nice?
So, 5,200 gold, $84 silver, something
far away from that to the upside or
downside to me is going to be more of a
signal of a breakout cuz that's been
kind of the steady numbers there. I'm
honestly shocked by the dollar. You
know, Miles, you mentioned it's up 0.1%.
You guys, we're in the middle of a
geopolitical conflict right here and the
dollar's not rallying. That's surprising
to me with the equities downturn. So,
Miles, you wanted to talk a little bit
more about the equities and we'll come
back to the metals, but what are you
seeing in terms of the stock market and
why do you think the dollar's not
confirming?
>> And where is the money going that's
leaving the stock market? No, I mean,
let's give the dollar the credit it's
due. You go back to the beginning of
February, you're under 96, we're up at
99, 99 and 1/2. You're still looking at
a 4% rise in the dollar. You're still
looking at a declining trend in the
dollar, too. We just looked at gold and
silver and we will want to come back to
that in a minute, but gold and silver
have a pretty clear defined rising trend
line, both of which are pretty close
down to the bottom of this rising range
that they're in. The dollar's doing the
same thing, it's just doing it to the
downside. So, you're looking at a
declining trend in the dollar
over the last about year or so. That's
what I was going to say, what time
frame? Yeah, because That's about April
of last year. Got you. Well, I mean,
obviously you can go a lot further back
than that cuz we did have that
significant decline in the dollar at the
beginning of last year from January to
April where it started to slowly
decline. Now, you're looking at an 11%
drop over the course of a couple months
and then it's been stair-stepping down
since then. Now, we're back up to the
top of that range right now where if you
start to see the dollar pushed to new
higher highs, well, then sure, we could
argue that maybe you see 105 again on
the dollar, 104, or something like that,
at least at where it would probably see
resistance again. So, yeah, the dollar,
if it were to push through a pretty
solid, but not guaranteed ceiling here,
we could have another 5 or 6% of growth
in the dollar with the understanding
that if it stays within the current
trend, dollar's probably turning around
and going back down in the near future.
Near future meaning over the next couple
days or weeks, and could be pushing down
sub-95 again if it's going to continue
this trend. And you bring up a good
point, Tory, cuz we are looking at a
pretty unstable position globally right
now. I mean, you look at some of the oil
prices, which have in some cases near
doubled overnight, and now they're
trying to find their footing in between
WTI crude and Brent and and US oil all
having significant run-up with a little
bit of a correction back down, and then
trying to reason out what's going to
happen to the Middle East and the oil
trade here as hopefully the dust settles
and boots don't keep kicking it up, but
there's a lot of uncertainty there, and
you see markets start to transition away
from the riskier assets into safer
assets as those types of things happen,
but they don't happen overnight, and I
think that's one of the big things to
keep in mind. And I think that's one of
the reasons why I always come back to my
old adage of
news doesn't move markets, it just
speeds up or slows down the direction
that it was going to trend anyway over
time. And you can get a news event that
maybe adds a couple percent one
direction or the other in a short term,
but it takes a long time to really turn
the ship a different direction
and a significant amount of expectation,
and you have to build up momentum. You
have to get many people on board, and
we'll just have to see how that ends up
playing out. Now, transitioning that
over to the equities market, most of
your equities markets, other than the
Dow transports, actually look like
they're topping out and potentially
going to
turn bearish, at least for a short
period of time. In fact, most of the
equities markets have short-term turned
bearish over the last couple of weeks,
and really showing a pattern of rolling
over.
So, it makes me wonder if there's
potentially something down the road, or
a line in the sand that, once breached,
you see a 10 or 15% haircut in the S&P,
in the Nasdaq, even in the Dow.
So, those are some of the things I'm
looking at here, with the dollar
starting to show strength, the equities
market starting to show weakness, or has
been showing weakness over the last
couple weeks. And gold and silver, which
just put in staggering highs in a very
short period of time, should be giving
us a cool-off period, and frankly, they
just aren't. They're not giving us a
cool-off period that most markets really
need to catch its breath and prepare for
the next move. Now, they're just
consolidating right now, Yeah.
>> getting ready, I think, in my opinion,
to launch into the spring highs. And I
think, fundamentally, too, a couple of
the reasons we talked about in our
pre-show meeting,
why the equities markets are cooling
off. You know, one is the shadow of how
much longer are we going to be in Iran?
We've only been there for a week, week
and a half, but that's definitely
weighing the market down.
Plus, the potential that the Democrat
Party is going to, in the midterms, take
back Congress.
That is going to hurt the markets
considerably, if that happens. Well, and
I I you saying that the dollar could
turn back down here, Miles, but I would
argue if
the equities roll over, that would
precipitate a dollar rally.
>> It usually does, yeah. Yeah, of course.
>> Yeah, usually the dollar's going to
resume its climb, and so we'll see what
ends up happening. And you could see a
short-term reversal in gold and silver
cuz that usually happens, too. But those
periods now, what used to be weeks for
them to recover or days, now it just
takes
hours for the metals to recover now.
Yeah, and we don't have much left in the
spring strong season. You don't think
so? Right. Well, I'm just saying
typically middle of May tends to be the
tipping point. Yeah. So, a couple
months.
>> Couple months. Yeah, so we've got all of
April. You know, look at last April. Oh.
It was great, and that's actually when
silver kind of bottomed and started its
climb. And if you look at the silver
chart from last April,
it's pretty amazing. Like, yes, we had
that January sort of manic melt-up, if
you will. But the trend from last April
hasn't been interrupted. No. Here we sit
at in at $85 an ounce, and Where were we
in April? Like, 28? Yeah, 30. 30.
>> And so, to me, it's like, well,
that's still showing some good strength.
At some point, we do see seasonal
weakness typically in the summer months.
>> Summer. It's quieter. But that's fine.
But all of this is just if So, the
dollar resumes its downturn if the
equities market stabilize and the
geopolitical scene stabilizes. The
dollar rallies if the equities markets
are
being fled from, and there is a flight
to safety. So, uncertainty equals
volatility, volatility equals safe
haven. And when people are looking for a
safe haven, they look for the US dollar
and they look for gold. Yes. Now, in the
immediate term, if the equities markets
do turn bearish, I think the speed
matters. Like, is it a really quick
event that is emotional, fear-driven, or
is it just this kind of snowball effect
over the course of weeks or a couple
months like it was what in 2022
where you saw that bear market and gold
and silver didn't really drop. But when
you get that precipitous fear-based
panic selling, it pulls gold and silver
down in the short term and creates an
amazing opportunity to buy. But you
can't wait for that.
>> No, no, no, no, you can't wait for that.
We don't even know that it's going to
happen. Exactly.
>> I'm just looking back with hindsight.
It's always 20/20. Right. Yeah.
Yeah, I mean you've also got to factor
in the digital trading platforms as
well. You know, it's funny you say,
"Hey, isn't the speed at which something
happens kind of dictates fear and
panic?" And it's almost like over the
last 15 years fear and panic is the
second thing that happens. You know, the
first thing that happens is an algorithm
tells you to sell. The second thing that
happens is
other algorithms tell you to sell
because of what the first algorithm did.
And then finally, once it's already down
20%, then the fear and panic sets in and
it says, "Okay, does the market at a
whole, you know, does the general public
get involved and then they start pulling
the trigger as well on liquidating
positions like we saw back in 2008?"
Right, the first 20% was digital, the
second 20 to 30% was panic. Now you've
got opportunities if you're liquid and
you've got cash available, but you're
right, it did pull gold down with it. I
think the big thing for me right now
when I'm looking at all these charts is
what happens if we start layering all
these things on top of each other? What
story are we trying to tell right now?
Well, the equities markets across the
board have been rolling over for the
last couple of weeks. Now, this could
just be a pause, but certainly the
geometry of the way the charts look
definitely look like we could be seeing
a 10 or 15% decline pending. 20, 25% in
your tech stocks and your more
aggressive positions, that something
like that may be around the corner.
We're in a world now where that happens
every handful of years. That's just
normal business nowadays for the average
stock portfolio. So, we're looking at
that. I'm looking at the average price
of a single-family detached home in the
United States sitting at the bottom of
its sort of trading channel. We're
looking at gold and silver, which have
been incredibly strong, but are
currently at the bottom of their
short-term trading channels. You're
looking at the US dollar, which is at
the top of its short-term trading
channel. So, everything has this are we
going to reverse and see continued
growth in gold, in silver, in real
estate, in the equities market, across
the board? Are we going to see people
move their money back up towards other
type of investable assets, or is
everybody just getting liquid? And
that's why I say, I think the next
couple weeks is going to be telling. We
see a breakout in the US dollar, we see
a breakdown in the equities, something
like that. We could see a short-term
pull 10 15% one direction or the other
depending on what we're looking at. And
if that happens, yeah, brings gold and
silver down with it. But if that second
step comes in, if the panic comes in and
says we have to get out of the Dow, we
have to get out of our equities
positions, we have to protect what we
have, that's when you see things that
are historically protective in nature,
like gold and silver, really have a good
solid run up. I mean, we've talked about
this for months now. Uh I've brought
this up multiple times on this show.
Gold quadrupled before the stock market
crashed in 2008. And then once the stock
market crashed and gold found bottom,
then it just doubled again from there.
But most of the real growth that we saw
in the precious metals market for people
who had been buying gold in the '90s and
early 2000s,
most of their growth was not 2008 market
crash to the high. It was everything
that happened before that, and then it
doubled again after that, which was
nice,
but most of the growth happened before.
So, I'm saying this cuz of what you said
a second ago, where it's like, "No, you
shouldn't wait for those declines. You
absolutely shouldn't."
Because the things you do leading into
the crisis are always more beneficial
than what you do while it's taking
place. You can't put your seatbelt on in
the middle of a car wreck. That's right,
which is why you move some silver to
gold, because in that instance it really
is about gold. It's the money metal, and
so you end up getting more ounces by
moving some silver to gold.
And I'm interested too to see what
happens with the ratio, but the equities
markets, you know, I think what the
story is being told here too from a
chart standpoint, laying these over each
other, watch and wait. I think all of
these markets are watching. So, there's
a lot of ambiguity from the White House
in terms of the time commitment with
Iran.
It's job is done. It's we're going to be
there for a few more weeks. It's no
boots on the ground. It's maybe some
boots on the ground. The markets don't
know. Even the oil market doesn't know.
Is the Strait of Hormuz going to be
sabotaged? Is it going to be closed? Is
it going to be defended by the US and
remain open? Are flows going to start
happening again? Is there max capacity
in storage already? Or are they fine?
Are we able to release stored oil from
reserves? That takes time. That takes
time. So, all of this is
>> to protect shipping in the Strait of
Hormuz takes time. Even though Lloyd's
of London is now reopening insurance
quotes for shipping through the straits.
This is not an overnight thing. No, it
is not. And so the markets necessarily
have to watch and meanwhile you do have
regular economic news coming in. People
almost don't even focus on it anymore.
What used to move the market now doesn't
a whole lot. The CPI, that was good news
today. It came in unchanged just at 2.4%
which is still too high. But what was at
4.4% was the national unemployment rate.
And that's not good.
>> And that's not good. So 2.4% for the CPI
was what was expected but it's still
higher than the Federal Reserve's target
of 2% right? Who by the way is meeting
next week. There's another FOMC meeting
next week. We'll have a rate
announcement next Wednesday when we
record. PPI came up a little bit. So
inflation is in one category unchanged
and another it's up a little bit but we
know it's going to be up next month
because you're going to absorb all of
this inflationary pressure in certain
sectors
from this conflict. And if we're still
in the throes of the conflict then the
markets will be far more concerned. But
the unemployment's not good. I mean you
got 7.6 million unemployed Americans,
long-term unemployed 1.9 million
which means the labor force
participation rate is only 62% working.
And you think okay well we're
reindustrializing the United States. No,
we're not. Manufacturing jobs have lost
98,000
jobs since February of 2025. So that's
just since Trump's inauguration.
We had 12,000 manufacturing jobs lost
just in February of this year alone. And
so that doesn't bode well for the
reindustrialization and the
manufacturing even though a lot of it
could be robotics. I think if you look
at what this administration is doing
there's a new refinery now
going to be breaking ground in
Brownsville, Texas for oil particularly
shale oil.
Uh you have the strategic mineral
smelter breaking ground in Clarksville,
Tennessee for 17 or 20 different
strategic rare earths and silver. So,
there are things that are happening that
we haven't done for decades. This is the
first new refinery in the US in 50
years. Same for the smelter. And I look
at what this administration has done.
They kicked China out of the Panama
Canal. They took Maduro out of
Venezuela.
Iran, we're in a week and a half into
Iran. That seems like it's going well,
knock on wood. The Ayatollah is gone,
too, obviously.
>> Right. Yeah, but they've got Ayatollah
light there now.
But Cuba literally is going to be going
lights out next week. Yeah, in all
likelihood, they've said Cuba is next. I
mean, they're not hiding that.
>> But that's lights out. I'm serious, they
will not be able to turn their lights on
next week. And if you think about what
the communist agenda, whether it's
Russia or the Chinese, they have spent
decades with their planning in
Venezuela, in Cuba, in Iran, in Panama.
In In a matter of just a few months,
this administration has turned the
tables. These things are completely
different. All these natural resources,
which a year ago we were saying we are
completely left out in the cold, it's
all coming this way.
I'm looking at the big picture saying,
"Yeah, I think short-term this
administration could easily lose the
midterms." I hope not. Because if we do,
this remarkable agenda
to put America on firm foundation, we're
done. Well, my entire life, it's been
Cuba. Not quite Iran, but I just can't
imagine a paradigm shift of all of those
problems going away. And it's not just
Cuba, I mean, but look at just Iran and
Venezuela, the mineral-rich ground. It's
not just about oil. Everybody wants to
talk about oil. No, I mean it's rare
earth minerals and silver and it's a
lot. And we were very vulnerable in
those areas and we have significantly
reduced our vulnerabilities by reducing
exposure to the uncertainties and
unknowns and the actions of these
dictators that are running those
countries Well, yeah. and aligning
themselves with Russia and Yeah. Very
deliberately and very strategically.
Yeah. I might add. Let's say it all
works. Two months from now, Iran is done
and we are seeing, hopefully, the people
of Iran enjoy some freedom that they
deserve. And Venezuela, same, you know,
freedom, have a chance to live a good
life. Then the US has to go back to
pushing the rock uphill. I mean, we're
going to be at $40 trillion national
debt. We've got a refi 10 trillion of
that this year.
So, I'm with Miles, short-term rally in
the dollar aside, We're in trouble. We
are in deep trouble. That's a good point
on the refinance of our debt. Like 10.8
is being refinanced. That's on top of
1.5 trillion in Treasuries that have to
be issued anew this year, right? So, at
higher interest rates. And it matters.
Like 3.5%
on interest on that is like 437 billion
just in interest payments. If you do it
4% is 500 billion. We could see the
dollar go below 90 and gold go to 6,000.
And I'm not talking in a matter of
years, I'm talking in a matter of
months.
>> Uh gold will go to 6,000 this year, for
sure, in my opinion. I think
>> Mine, too. And the dollar is due for
what Miles predicted to be a downturn.
So, the geopolitical thing is certainly
worth watching. For now, only gold is
gold and it matters in the world. And
you really do need to reduce
counterparty risk and be careful of
hypothecation. Like make sure if you
have stored metals or paper metals that
they're not promised to somebody else
also. They're not leveraged. That
doesn't count. Mohamed El-Erian, the
economist, who's a brilliant guy, came
out and said, "Look, unemployment's a
problem, inflation is a problem,
economic stagflation is a problem, and
there's too much competition for bonds
without enough demand. The bond market
is really suspect." And he was at PIMCO.
I mean, he knows. Globally, only gold is
gold, and for you the listener that owns
it, well done and stack the chips. So,
once again, we appreciate y'all joining
us for Golden Rule Radio. If you liked
what you heard, we encourage you to head
on over to our website. We can always be
found at mcalvany.com. That's m c a l v
a n y.com.
And as always, if you like to discuss
your personal portfolio with one of the
advisors here at McAlvany Precious
Metals, you can reach us at
1-800-525-9556.
Have a great week.